Guide to the Naval History Society Collection 1721-1995 (bulk 1781-1936) MS 439
New-York Historical Society
- Series 21. Caspar F. Goodrich (1862-1933)
  1924: Writes memoir "Rope yarns from the old navy"
  1925 Dies, Princeton, New Jersey
  1931: Naval History Society publishes "Rope yarns from the old navy," edited by James Barnes, as eleventh volume of its publications.
  1933: Mrs. Goodrich donates the manuscript of "Rope yarns" to the Naval History Society
  1936: Eleanor Goodrich (Mrs. C.T Davis) donates Goodrich collection to the Naval History Society
  The collection is arranged in five subseries:
  Subseries II. Naval War College lectures and lecture notes
  Subseries III. Writings
  Subseries IV. James Goodrich journal transcripts
  Subseries V. Bound volumes
  - Subseries I: Correspondence (1871-1918)
    The subseries consists mainly of official correspondence received, including orders to report to ships, permissions for leave, administration of the Torpedo Board, service on various courts martial, and assignments to lecture at the Naval War College. The letters sent are mostly typescript carbons with some letterpress copies, and include official reports filed on operations and cruises, providing details of the responsibilities of a ship's commander in this period. John Meigs's January 1909 letters discuss the formation of a naval historical society and in that year John Sanford Barnes sends draft bylaws of the Naval Historical Society, comparing it to Britain's Naval Records Society. The last document was found in the original Correspondence box and is not in Goodrich's handwriting; it may have been written by New-York Historical Society librarian Dorothy Barck.
    - Letters sent, 1871-1906 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters sent: Draft to Ben Lamberton, 1895 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters received, 1863 -1878 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters received, 1881 -1884 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters received, 1885 - 1887 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters received, 1888 - 1889 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters received, 1890 - 1893 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters received, 1894 - 1895 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters received, 1896 - 1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters received, 1903 - 1906 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters received, 1909, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Printed enclosure: H.R. 8476, Committee on Naval Affairs, U.S. House of Representatives, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Note on post-war planning, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Subseries II. Naval War College lectures and lecture notes (1862-1904)
    The subseries includes notes, handwritten drafts, and final versions (mostly carbon typescripts) of lectures Goodrich presented at the Naval War College, as well as notes on other topics. Also included are a newspaper clipping and a list of personal items, perhaps from the Goodrich residence, found with the lecture materials. "The Problem of 96" is one of the annual examinations by College cadets of a challenge in coastal defense: the 1896 one looked at a specific part of nearby Narragansett Bay. This is an early precursor of the theoretical "war games" the College famously initiated.
    The numbered lectures were delivered in order as part of a series on famous international naval encounters, from the Battle of Sluys in 1340 to Drake's destruction of King Phillip's fleet in Cadiz Harbor in 1587, Napoleon's Nile Campaign of 1798, and the 1827 Battle of Navarino during the Greek War of Independence. These form the backdrop for Goodrich's final multipart lecture on Dewey's engagement in Manila during the Spanish-American War, which had occurred only three years before these lectures. It is unclear if the material on the Army's landing in Cuba formed part of this presentation.
    The lecture notes are arranged chronologically and the numbered lectures in order as noted on them and their original packaging. Some lectures' accompanying graphic materials (maps and photoreproductions probably used in the preparation of lantern slides) were pinned to the lecture text; these have been separated, numbered by page on which they appeared, and housed by lecture. The notes' original envelopes are in separate folders; they may date any time from the lectures in 1901 to the collection's donation to the Naval History Society in 1933.
    - Extract from "Fortifications and Sea Coast Defenses," Congressional Committee on Military Affairs, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Lists of personal items, probably 1890s (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Problem of 96: Eggemoggin Reach; copy of Admiral Mahan letter to Taylor on the subject, 1895 July 19, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper clipping on privateering, 1896 April 16 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letter on armored cruisers from Admiral W.S. Schley, 1896 July 23 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Naval War College documents: Elements of a "War Chart and Defense Plan"; definition of art of war; document on international law, 1896, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Letter defining Mediterranean compass variations 1798; notes on Egyptian campaign of 1798, 1901 Jan 22, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - First lecture: Battle of Sluys. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - First lecture: Battle of Sluys. Photoreproductions, maps, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Second lecture: Singeing the King of Spain's Beard: Cadiz, 1587. Draft, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Second lecture: Singeing the King of Spain's Beard: Cadiz, 1587. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Third lecture: Blake at Porto Farina. Draft, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Third lecture: Blake at Porto Farina. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Third lecture: Blake at Porto Farina. Maps and photoreproductions., 1901 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Fourth lecture: Blake's last fight - Santa Cruz de Teneriffe, April 20, 1627. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Fifth lecture: The Nile Campaign I. The Pursuit. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Sixth lecture: The Battle of the Nile II. The Attack. Draft, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Sixth lecture: The Battle of the Nile II. The Attack. Text, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Sixth lecture: The Battle of the Nile II. The Attack. Maps and reproductions, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Seventh lecture: The Battle of Navarino. Draft., 1901 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Dewey at Manila: Notes, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Dewey at Manila: I. Introduction. II. Strained Relations. III. Dewey's Objectives. IV. Authorities. V. American Preparations, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Dewey at Manila: VI. The Opposing Forces. VII. Spanish Preparations. VIII. Spanish Accounts of the Battle, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Dewey at Manila: IX. American Accounts of the Battle. X. The Finish, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - The landing of the army in Cuba, circa 1901 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Assorted lecture notes. Envelope, 1904 (Box OS 1, Folder 9)
    - Second lecture. Singeing of the King of Spain's Beard. Envelope, Undated (Box OS 1, Folder 10)
    - Seventh lecture. The Battle of Navarino. Envelope, Undated (Box OS 1, Folder 11)
    - Seventh lecture. The Battle of Navarino. Map blueprints, Undated (Box OS 1, Folder 12)
    - Sixth lecture. Battle of the Nile. Envelopes, Undated (Box OS 3, Folder 3)
  - Subseries III. Writings (1901-1933)
    The subseries includes notes and final versions of Goodrich's writings, apart from the lectures he delivered at the Naval War College, including various topics in naval warfare, an address on establishing a naval training facility in San Diego, and his 1924 memoirs. The latter includes a typescript with handwritten emendations probably by James Barnes, who edited the work for publication by the Naval History Society ("Rope yarns from the old navy," published by J.J. Little & Ives Co., as the eleventh volume of the Society's publications), and a final clean version incorporating those changes. The memoirs are an affectionate look at his early service in the Navy, which he describes as "coincident with the great changes from sail to steam; from wooden frigates to steel dreadnoughts; from smooth bore muzzle loaders to breech loading rifled cannon; from man power to electricity."
    - Logistics, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Coast defense, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Label from wrapper for writings on coast defense and logistics, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Navigation, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Interior water communication, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Scouting for the U.S.S. Tacony, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Dutch - French - English Wars of the 17th Century, [1901] (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Extracts from G.B. Mundy's 1830 Biography of Admiral Rodney, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Confidential report of Gunnery Information Obtained During a Visit to England - British Battle Practice", 1905 June (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Comments to San Diego Chamber of Commerce about establishing a naval training station, circa 1916 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - In memoriam: Tribute to Stephen Bleecker Luce, published by the Naval History Society, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": Cover page, foreword, comments, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": I. How I Entered the Navy. II. At the Naval Academy During the Civil War. III. Some Experiences as a Midshipman, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": IV. Goldsborough. V. My First Foreign Port. VI. Mediterranean Cruise, Concluded. VII. With Farragut, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": VIII. In the South Atlantic, 1869-1871. IX. A Remote Island Community. X. St. Paul de Loando - St. Helena - Ascension. XI. In Asiatic Waters, 1875-1878, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": XII. Another European Cruise. XIII. Another European Cruise (Concluded). XIV. The Last of My Sailing Ships: 1. The Jamestown., 1924 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": XV. 2. The Constellation. XVI. Bluejackets of the Old Navy, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": Complete revised typescript, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "Rope Yarns from the Old Navy": Typescript box, presented to the Naval History Society March 29, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Series IV. James Goodrich journal transcripts (undated)
    Scope and Contents note
    The subseries consists of undated notes in Goodrich's hand, and a typed transcript, from the logs of Captain James Goodrich (dated 1796-1853) aboard various vessels, including Confederacy. These may be related to the publication in Journal of American History (IV, II, pp. 273-280, 1910) of "First Commerce Under American Flag," by William Goodrich (grandson of James and brother of Caspar F.), which documents James Goodrich's claims against the French government for restitution of goods seized on a voyage.
    - "Notes from the log of the Confederacy from London to Madeira to China (in which James Goodrich sailed), 1796 Jan 10 - 1797 June 9, Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "Miscellaneous abstracts from journal on board the ship Fame etc. of Capt. James Goodrich, London to New Orleans", 1800-1801, Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Random notes from the journals of Captain James W. Goodrich", 1823 - 1853, Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Typed transcript from James Goodrich logs: Conditions in Whampoa, China (probably aboard Galaxy), circa 1835, Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Subseries V. Bound volumes
    The subseries consists of a scrapbook of newspaper clippings on the Spanish-American War.
    - Scrapbook of clippings on the Spanish-American War, 1898 (Volume 1)
- Series 22. Great Britain, Navy (1769-1786)
  The collection includes original lists from the Royal Navy that provide detailed information on ships and their outfitting, and transcripts of Admiralty outgoing letters bound by the Naval History Society. The latter form the basis of the Society's third volume of publications in 1913: "The Dispatches of Molyneux Shuldham, Vice-Admiral of the Blue and Commander in Chief of his Brittanic Majesty's Ships in North America, Jan-July 1776," edited by Robert W. Neeser and printed by DeVinne Press, New York.
  - "A List of His Majesty's Royal Navy, Navy Office", 1769 (Volume 1)
  - "A Correct list of the Royal Navy for the 1st of January 1786 with the dimentions and value of the hulls, masts, yards, sails, guns, shot, anchor, cable furniture, etc." (Volume 2)
  - "Great Britain Admirality Secretary's Department Out-Letters, Letters, Orders and Instructions and Secret Letters to Vice Admiral Graves April 8, 1774 - April 25, 1776/ Vols. 99-100, 548-551, 1332-1333, 1774-1776", Undated (Volume 3)
  - "Great Britain Admirality Secretary's Department Out-Letters, Letters, Orders and Instructions and Secret Letters to Rear or Vice Admiral Shuldham July 19, 1775-Sept 6, 1776/ vols. 99-101, 550-552, 1333", Undated (Volume 4)
- Series 23. Samuel Dana Greene (1869-1883, 1931)
  The collection consists of letters, orders, and other official communications to, and both manuscript and letterpress copies of letters from, Greene while in command of various vessels, as well as receipted bills for personal and chandlery supplies for the ships. The documents from Admiral Turner are mostly printed circulars, and Volume 1 includes a letter to Naval History Society librarian Dorothy Barck providing details about the Greene family, from the Boston book and autograph dealer who sold these manuscript materials to the Society. Volume 2 provides detailed information on Saranac's officers, rigging, crew, and movements via its log, while the volumes from USS Juniata and Monongahela detail requests for enlistment and re-enlistment, reports of missing sailors, and other daily shipboard operations. Correspondence to the Secretary of the Navy is addressed to George M. Robeson (1869 - March 1877) and Richard W. Thompson (April 1887 - 1880).
  Samuel Dana Greene (1840-1884) served as USS Monitor's only executive officer, under five different commanders, assuming command after Captain Worden was wounded in the engagement at Hampton Roads with CSS Virginia (originally Merrimack) on March 9, 1862. Although criticized for permitting Merrimack's retreat, he acted in accord with the orders of both President Lincoln and Assistant Secretary of the Navy Gustavus V. Fox (Series 17), confining Monitor to a defensive role. Between 1866 and 1884 he served in various capacities at the US Naval Academy. From 1868 to 1871 he saw service with the Pacific Squadron aboard USS Saranac to Chile under the command of Admiral Turner; commanded USS Juniata of the European Station in 1875-1876 and the training ship USS Monongahela off the East Coast from 1876-1877; and was in command of cadet engineers from Annapolis aboard USS Despatch from 1882 to 1884. He killed himself at the Portsmouth Navy Yard, attributed to anxiety over an article on the Monitor/Virginia engagement he was preparing for publication.
  - General Orders and Circulars from Rear Admiral Thomas Turner, USN commanding the Pacific Fleet, 1869-1870, 1931 (Volume 1)
  - Watch, Quarters & Station Bills, USS Saranac, Pacific fleet, 1870 (Volume 2)
  - General correspondence, USS Juniata, 1875 January 25 - 1876 February 12 (Volume 3)
  - Correspondence with the Secretary of the Navy from USS Juniata and USS Monongahela, 1875 January 25 - 1877 July 18 (Volume 4)
  - Telegrams sent from USS Juniata and Monongahela, 1875 January 28 - 1877 June 9 (Volume 5)
  - Letters received aboard USS Juniata and USS Monongahela, 1876 May 23 - 1877 January 31 (Volume 6)
  - Letter press copies USS Monongahela, 1876-1877 (Volume 7)
  - Letters received on USS Monongahela, 1877 January 23 -July 23 (Volume 8)
  - Receipted Bills for Personal Expenses, 1879 January 30 - 1881 December 31 (Volume 9)
  - Letters received on USS Despatch, 1882 July 10 -1883 June 27 (Volume 10)
- Series 24. Theodore P. Greene (1863-1864)
  The collection consists of a single volume of copies of outgoing letters from and one incoming letter to Captain Theodore P. Greene while aboard USS Mercedita, USS Santiago de Cuba, and USS San Jacinto in 1863 and 1864. The volume shows a bookplate from the library of Richard Worsam Meade 4th, son of Rear Admiral Richard Worsam Meade 3rd (see Series 31). The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
  Theodore P. Greene (1809-1887) was appointed midshipman in 1826 and served on various vessels in the Mediterranean and Pacific. In 1860 he assumed command of the Mare Island Naval Shipyard near San Francisco, California. He was promoted to captain in 1862 and served aboard USS Mercedita in the North Atlantic Blockading Squadron from Beaufort, North Carolina. He commanded USS Santiago de Cuba and later USS San Jacinto in the East Gulf Blocking Squadron, intercepting vessels including Confederate ships flying English colors. He was appointed a member of the Board of Visitors at the US Naval Academy in May, 1868, and later that year assumed command of Pensacola Navy Yard until his retirement in 1872.
  - Letter book of Captain Theodore P. Greene, U.S. N., U.S Ships Mercedita 1863; Santiago de Cuba 1863; San Jacinto, 1864, 1863 June - 1864 July (Volume 1)
- Series 25. Lewis Randolph Hamersly (1870, 1872, 1878; bulk, 1870)
  The collection consists of one volume of 289 letters received after the publication of Hamersly's 1870 and 1878 editions of "The records of living officers of the U.S. Navy and Marine Corps, compiled from official sources." They include orders to purchase the publications and updates to officers' records in the previous edition, sometimes annotated on clippings taken from it.
  Lewis Randolph Hamersly (1847-1910) served in the Navy from 1862 to 1866 and in the Marine Corps from 1866 to 1869 before entering the publishing trade. His "Records of living officers," published by J.B. Lippincott and others in seven editions from 1870 to 1902, detailed the full records of living officers in the US Navy and Marine Corps. After establishing his own publishing firm, he published later editions of this and other reference works including "A naval encyclopedia" in 1881, "List of officers of the Navy of the United States and of the Marine Corps from 1775 to 1900" in 1901, and "First citizens of the republic" in 1906.
  - Letters, Officers of U.S. Navy, 1870, 1872, 1878 (Volume 1)
- Series 26. Lt. Robert William Henderson (1907-1908)
  The series consists of a scrapbook of materials collected during the American Fleet's 1907-1908 cruise to the Pacific by Lieutenant Robert William Henderson (1877-1921), who served as Admiral W. H. Emory's flag lieutenant (aide de camp) during part of the cruise. It includes invitations to balls, dinners, dances, and other social gatherings; passes for private clubs, events, and ship access; place cards, programs, menus, and dance cards; caricatures and uncaptioned photographs, including some of earthquake damage in Messina, Sicily.
  The United States battle fleet's first ever global circumnavigation, involving some 14,000 sailors and stops in 20 international ports, departed Hampton Roads, Virginia, on December 16, 1907. The 16 battleships and escorts (nicknamed "The Great White Fleet") made stops in Trinidad and Cuba before sailing along South America's east coast, through the Straits of Magellan, and north up the west coast to rendezvous in Magdalena Bay, Mexico. The fleet arrived in San Francisco in May. From there it called at Honolulu, Hawaii; Auckland, New Zealand; Sydney, Melbourne, and Perth, Australia; Manila; Tokyo and Yokohama, Japan; Amoy, China; Hong Kong; and reached Suez, Egypt, on January 3, 1909. In Italy, crew members offered aid to victims of a recent earthquake there. The fleet departed Italy January 9, 1909, making a stop in Gibraltar and arriving at Hampton Roads on February 22.
  - US Navy World Cruise Scrapbook, 1907-1909 (Volume 1)
- Series 27. Isaac Hull (1798-1841)
  The series comprises logbooks, letter books, combined journal and letter book volumes, and orders received by Captain Isaac Hull aboard various vessels and while in command of Navy Yards in Boston, Portsmouth, and Washington.
  The USS Constitution material includes logbooks while it was under the command of Samuel Nicholson and Silas Talbot (Volume 1), and then under Hull's command, including immediately before its August 1812 engagement with Guerriere. Its 1810-1811 logbook (Volume 3) includes "Commander Rodgers' Rules for Sparring and Rigging Frigates;" dimensions of British vessels built and launched 1809; dimensions of the USF President, a bomb ketch, a gun boat, US Brig Hornet, US Brig Congress, and US Brig Chesapeake, plus "an indent [order or requisition] of articles by various personnel, presumably of a frigate."
  The letter books include copies of outgoing correspondence from Hull to Commodore John Rodgers, Secretary of the Navy Paul Hamilton, and others (Volumes 2 and 4) while Hull was commanding USS Constitution; to Navy Secretaries William Jones and Benjamin W. Crowninshield, Navy agent Samuel Storer, Commodore William Bainbridge (see Series 1), and others (Volumes 6 and 7), while he was commanding Portsmouth Navy Yard; to Navy Secretary Samuel Southard and others (Volume 8), General Simon Bolivar, General Jose Ramon Rodil, Michael Hogan, and other US officials in South America (Volume 9), Secretary of the Navy James K. Paulding and others (Volume 14), and officers in the Mediterranean Squadron (Volume 15) while he was commanding USS Ohio and USS United States. The 1823-1827 order book (Volume 10) includes letters to officers under his command on the Pacific coast of South America while he commanded USS United States.
  The 1829-1831 and 1829-1835 letter books (Volumes 12 and 13) include correspondence to the Secretary of the Navy, Navy Commissioners, and others while Hull commanded the Navy Yard in Washington.
  Two volumes combine letters with other materials. Volume 11 includes letters sent (August 10, 1824, to March 10, 1837), which are indexed on pp. 69-72, with orders sent (October 1, 1838, to October 12, 1840) to officers commanding vessels in the Mediterranean Squadron under Hull's leadership. Volume 17 includes a range of letters from October, 1838, to July, 1841, while Hull commanded USS Ohio as well as log entries, miscellaneous remarks, and copies of letters dated April 15 to August 2, 1841.
  Portions of the collection are available on microfilm.
  1773: Isaac Hull born Derby, Connecticut, March 9
  1798: Commissioned fourth lieutenant
  1798-1800: Aboard frigate Constitution under Commodores Samuel Nicholson and Silas Talbot
  1801: Takes charge of Constitution
  1803: Commands USS Enterprise
  1804: Promoted master commandant; as commander of brig Argus participates with Commodore Edward Preble's Mediterranean squadron in the war against the Barbary States
  1806: Promoted captain; in Connecticut contracts for and superintends building of four gunboats
  1809: Aboard USS John Adams and USS Chesapeake
  1810: Commands USS Constitution
  1811: Conveys Joel Barlow, newly appointed US minister to France, and carries currency to Holland to pay interest on debt
  1812: War is declared against Great Britain, June 20
  1812: Sails from Annapolis July 12 to join squadron of Commodore Rodgers at New York.
  1812: Constitution engages and ruins British frigate Guerriere on August 19 while sustaining minimal damage and earns sobriquet "Old Ironsides"; Hull receives surrender of Captain Dacres
  1812: Receives Congressional gold medal; Constitution's crew receives cash awards
  1813: Commands Boston Navy Yard and Portsmouth Navy Yard
  1815: Appointed to Board of Navy Commissioners
  1824-1827: Commodore of Pacific Squadron flagship United States protecting American shipping and commercial interests
  1829-1835: Commands Washington Navy Yard